Guide to the Commission on University Governance Records, 1969-1971 UA.06.02.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Commission on University Governance records
1969-1971
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Commission on University Governance
UA.06.02.0001
2.5 Linear Feet
The Commission on University Governance at Duke University was created in April 1969 by Chancellor pro tem Barnes Woodhall. The group was charged with studying changes in university organization nationwide to create a model for administration at Duke. The group also focused on increasing student participation in university governance. The records include minutes, memoranda, correspondence, and reports produced by the Commission on University Governance, as well as reports, clippings, and other printed matter gathered by the Commission for reference purposes. The Commission published its findings and recommendations in three "Interim Reports," concerning the Board of Trustees, the Central Administration, and Departmental Governance. English.
2 boxes
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
Acquisitions Information
Received 23 January 1974 from the Chancellor's Office as A74-68.
Historical Note
The late 1960s was a time of rapid change at American colleges and universities, as most experienced a surge of politicization by student activists; at Duke, this was most clearly exemplified in the Allen Building takeover of February 13, 1969. In response both to this local event and to national trends in higher education, the Faculty Committee on Student Concerns, the Executive Committee of the Academic Council, and the Student-Faculty-Administrative Council (SFAC) recommended the creation of a Commission on University Governance. In April 1969 Chancellor pro tem Barnes Woodhall appointed this committee, with the hopes that future demonstrations similar to the Allen Building takeover might be avoided if effective official opportunities for student participation in university governance could be established. The Commission on University Governance was therefore charged with the task of studying changes in university organization nationwide, focusing particularly on student participation in governance, and making recommendations for Duke accordingly.
Members of the Commission eventually agreed that this purpose was best accomplished by dividing university governance into three categories: departmental governance, the central university administration, and the Board of Trustees. The latter body was already the subject of a study by a Board of Trustees Special Committee headed by Brantley Watson, and the Commission coordinated its efforts with the Watson Committee. The Commission on University Governance also worked simultaneously and cooperatively with the Chancellor's Advisory Committee, "The Committee of Twelve," which replaced the SFAC as the forum for airing Duke community grievances and which was meant to advise the administration concerning potentially volatile campus issues. The Commission on University Governance met 34 times between October 27, 1969 and May 17, 1970, at which time it adjourned for the school year and was never reactivated.
Scope and Content Note
The records of the Commission on University Governance span the years 1969 to 1971, with most of the material dating from 1969-1970 academic year. The collection is organized into two series: materials created by the Commission, and materials collected by the Commission.
The records generated by the Commission on University Governance consist primarily of minutes and transcripts of its official meetings, including supplementary materials distributed for discussion at these meetings. Typed transcript drafts exist for meetings 1 through 19, and this series contains minutes for all 34 meetings. Also included in this series are two copies of each of the Commission's three Interim Reports (Board of Trustees, Central Administration, and Departmental Governance), as well as drafts of these reports. Other official Commission records include information on the Commission's members and clippings from the Chronicle, Durham Morning Herald, and Durham Sun dated September 30, 1969 to April 16, 1970 concerning the work of the Commission. Correspondence not included with Commission minutes is divided into two folders: 1) letters dated April to September 1969, all regarding the establishment of the Commission, and 2) official correspondence dated after that time, including a January 1970 introduction to the Commission's activities for new Duke President Terry Sanford and a January 1971 response to the Commission's Interim Reports from the Provost.
The Commission on University Governance amassed a significant collection of reference materials for use in formulating its reports, which are roughly arranged into subseries. It appears that members of the Commission twice attempted to catalog and collate these materials, as two indexes entitled "Materials on Hand" and "Table of Contents" are a part of this series. However, neither index is accompanied by a complete set of the materials listed on it. To preserve original order, the sections of listed materials that are present have been identified and retained, even when they duplicate each other. Printed matter that was not a part of either of these subseries falls into two categories: reports and other matter from Duke committees, schools, and organizations, and printed matter that was created by other universities and organizations. This series also contains several bibliographies, arranged both by subject and by format, as well as periodical abstracts, alphabetized by author, donated to the Commission from the Special Committee on Student Residential Life. Also present in this series are the complete minutes of the Chancellor's Advisory Committee, known as the Committee of Twelve, which met nineteen times between October 1969 and March 1970, when it was disbanded.
University Archives also has catalogued copies of the Commission's three Interim Reports:
Board of Trustees - 378.756 D877CTR
Central Administration - 378.756 D877CGO
Departmental Governance - 378.756 D877CDG
Related Material
Office of the Chancellor records: Committee files.
University Archives, Duke University.
Charles B. Wade papers.
University Archives, Duke University.
Student participation in administration; College administrators; Universities and colleges -- Departments; Universities and colleges -- Administration -- Evaluation; Universities and colleges -- Administration; Woodhall, Barnes; Duke University. Commission on University Governance; Duke University. Commission on University Governance; Duke University. Board of Trustees; Duke University -- Administration
- Commission Records, 1969-1971
  - Meeting 1 - Oct. 27, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Meeting 2 - Nov. 3, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Meeting 3 - Nov. 9, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Meeting 4 - Nov. 16, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Meeting 5 - Nov. 22, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Meeting 6 - Dec. 1, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Meeting 7 - Dec. 5, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Meeting 8 - Dec. 7, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Meeting 9 - Dec. 14, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Meeting 10 - Jan. 4, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Meeting 11 - Jan. 11, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Meeting 12 - Jan. 18, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Meeting 13 - Jan. 25, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Meeting 14 - Jan. 28, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Meeting 15 - Jan. 29, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Meeting 16 - Feb. 1, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Meeting 17 - Feb. 5, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Meeting 18 - Feb. 18, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Meeting 19 - Feb. 8, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Meeting 20 - Feb. 22, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Meeting 21 - Mar. 1, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Meeting 22 - Mar. 8, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Meeting 23 - Mar. 15, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Meeting 24 - Mar. 22, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Meeting 25 - Mar. 30, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Meeting 26 - Apr. 5, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Meeting 27 - Apr. 12, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Meeting 28 - Apr. 14, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Meeting 29 - Apr. 16, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Meeting 30 - Apr. 19, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Meeting 31 - Apr. 26, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Meeting 32 - Apr. 30, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Meeting 33 - May 10, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Meeting 34 - May 17, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Interim Report: Board of Trustees (Box 1)
  - Interim Report: Board of Trustees - Drafts (Box 1)
  - Interim Report: Central Administration (Box 1)
  - Interim Report: Central Administration - Drafts (Box 1)
  - Interim Report: Departmental Governance (Box 1)
  - Interim Report: Departmental Governance - Drafts (Box 1)
  - Clippings (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (regarding establishment of the Commission) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (Official - Misc.) (Box 1)
  - Membership Information (Box 1)
- Reference Materials, 1969-1971
  - Reference Materials - "Bound"
    - Table of Contents (Box 2)
    - I. Duke Materials (Box 2)
    - II. Antioch Study (Box 2)
    - III. Berkeley Study (Box 2)
    - IV. Wisconsin Study (Box 2)
    - VI. Faculty (Box 2)
    - VII. Speeches, etc. (Box 2)
    - [XII] "Not Bound" (Box 2)
  - Reference "Materials in Hand"
    - 10. Theory, Administration, and Faculty (Box 2)
    - 13. Student Participation in Duke Decision Making (Box 2)
    - 14. Student Unrest (Box 2)
    - 15. Boards of Trustees (Box 2)
    - 16. Report of the Times, 1964-1969 (Box 2)
  - Reference Materials - Bibliographies
    - Bibliography - Subject Index (Box 2)
    - Bibliography - Book Indexes (Box 2)
    - Bibliography - Periodical Indexes (Box 2)
  - Duke Reference Materials
    - GSA Questionnaire on Departmental Governance (Box 2)
    - "University Governance in a Changing Political Context" paper by Wade Norris (Duke Ugrad) (Box 2)
    - Watson Report ("Functions and Organization of the Board of Trustees"), Nov. 1, 1969 (Box 2)
    - Special Student/Faculty Committee on Increased Student Participation in Law School Decision-making (Box 2)
    - Misc. Duke Reports (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Reference Materials
    - AAUP and AAAS materials (Box 2)
    - Cornell Report (Box 2)
    - Cornell Bibliography (Box 2)
    - Clippings (Box 2)
    - Periodical Abstracts (A-L) (Box 2)
    - Periodical Abstracts (M-Z and university experiments) (Box 2)
  - Chancellor's Advisory Committee Minutes
    - Membership Information (Box 2)
    - Meetings 1-4 (Oct. 1969) (Box 2)
    - Meetings 5-8 (Nov. 1969) (Box 2)
    - Meetings 9-12 (Dec. 1969) (Box 2)
    - Meetings 13-14 (Jan. 1970) (Box 2)
    - Meetings 15-17 (Feb. 1970) (Box 2)
    - Meetings 18-19 (Mar. 1970) (Box 2)